<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="sayuki_project_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright (c) 2026 Sayuki contributors. Licensed under MIT OR Apache-2.0.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="per-surface project affinity">
    This protocol lets a trusted first-party client declare, before a toplevel
    maps, which Sayuki project (canvas) a surface belongs to and where it should
    sit in that canvas's free-floating coordinate space.

    Sayuki organizes windows as a viewport over an unbounded canvas, one canvas
    per project. Without this protocol the compositor can only guess a surface's
    project affinity heuristically (by app_id or pid) after the fact; this
    protocol makes placement race-free and authoritative at map time.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
    phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
    corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can only
    be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
  </description>

  <interface name="zsayuki_project_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="factory for project-surface objects">
      The global object, advertised only to trusted first-party clients. It
      creates zsayuki_project_surface_v1 objects that tag a wl_surface with
      project affinity.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_constructed" value="0"
             summary="the wl_surface already has a project-surface object"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="get_project_surface">
      <description summary="assign project affinity to a surface">
        Create a project-surface object for the given wl_surface. The surface
        must have, or be about to be given, the xdg_toplevel role.

        Requesting a second project-surface for a wl_surface that already has one
        is a protocol error (already_constructed).
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zsayuki_project_surface_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the manager object. Project-surface objects created by this
        manager are unaffected.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zsayuki_project_surface_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="project affinity for a single surface">
      Declares the project a toplevel belongs to and its persistent canvas
      coordinates. All set_ requests must be sent before the surface's first
      commit (analogous to assigning an xdg role); sending them after the
      surface has mapped is a protocol error (already_mapped).

      After placement the compositor reports the authoritative project name and
      canvas position the surface actually landed on.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_mapped" value="0"
             summary="a set_ request was sent after the surface committed"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="set_project">
      <description summary="choose the project canvas">
        Set the name of the project (canvas) this surface should live on. If no
        project with this name is known the compositor places the surface on the
        current project instead and reports the fallback via the assigned event.

        Must be sent before the first commit of the wl_surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="name" type="string"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_canvas_position">
      <description summary="set persistent canvas coordinates">
        Set the surface's top-left position in the project canvas's
        free-floating coordinate space. The compositor may clamp the value to
        its canvas pan limits.

        Must be sent before the first commit of the wl_surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_rule_hint">
      <description summary="provide a placement rule hint">
        Provide a free-form window-rule hint (for example "floating", "pin", or
        "fullscreen") applied at map time. Unknown keys are ignored.

        Must be sent before the first commit of the wl_surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="key" type="string"/>
      <arg name="value" type="string"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the project-surface object">
        Destroy the project-surface object. Affinity already applied at map time
        is retained; it is not re-evaluated on later commits.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="assigned">
      <description summary="authoritative project assignment">
        Sent once the surface has been placed, carrying the name of the project
        canvas it actually landed on (which may differ from a requested but
        unknown project name).
      </description>
      <arg name="project_name" type="string"/>
    </event>

    <event name="canvas_position">
      <description summary="authoritative canvas position">
        Sent once the surface has been placed, carrying its final top-left
        position in the project canvas after any clamping.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
