<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="sayuki_canvas_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright (c) 2026 Sayuki contributors. Licensed under MIT OR Apache-2.0.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="unbounded-canvas viewport observer and controller">
    Sayuki presents windows on an unbounded canvas viewed through a per-output
    camera (viewport). This protocol exposes that camera to trusted first-party
    clients: observer events drive minimap and overview surfaces, and controller
    requests let a shell pan, zoom, and focus the camera. No standard protocol
    models a camera over an unbounded canvas.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
    phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
    corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can only
    be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
  </description>

  <interface name="zsayuki_canvas_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="factory for per-output canvas objects">
      The global object, advertised only to trusted first-party clients. It
      creates zsayuki_canvas_v1 objects, each scoped to one wl_output.
    </description>

    <request name="get_canvas">
      <description summary="observe and control one output's camera">
        Create a canvas object scoped to the given wl_output. The object
        receives observer events for that output's camera and accepts controller
        requests that drive it.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zsayuki_canvas_v1"/>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the manager object. Canvas objects created by this manager are
        unaffected.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zsayuki_canvas_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="one output's camera over the canvas">
      Observer events report the camera state and the windows visible on this
      output's canvas; they are emitted in atomic batches terminated by done,
      mirroring wl_output. Controller requests drive the same internal viewport
      operations as Sayuki's keybindings and IPC, so the protocol is just an
      additional caller.
    </description>

    <event name="viewport">
      <description summary="camera location and zoom">
        The top-left canvas coordinate shown on this output and the zoom factor.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
      <arg name="zoom" type="fixed"/>
    </event>

    <event name="window_geometry">
      <description summary="a window's canvas geometry">
        Position, size, and focus state of a window on this canvas, keyed by its
        stable window id. Re-sent for every visible window in a batch.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
      <arg name="width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"/>
      <arg name="focused" type="uint" summary="non-zero if keyboard-focused"/>
    </event>

    <event name="window_removed">
      <description summary="a window left this canvas">
        The window with this id is no longer present on the canvas.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="uint"/>
    </event>

    <event name="project_changed">
      <description summary="the canvas shown on this output changed">
        The output now shows a different project's canvas.
      </description>
      <arg name="name" type="string"/>
    </event>

    <event name="done">
      <description summary="end of an atomic update batch">
        All preceding events since the last done form one atomic update; a
        client should apply them together and repaint once.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="pan">
      <description summary="set the absolute camera position">
        Move the camera so that x,y is the canvas coordinate at the output's
        top-left corner. Clamped to the compositor's pan limits.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
    </request>

    <request name="pan_by">
      <description summary="pan the camera by a delta">
        Move the camera by dx,dy canvas units. Clamped to the compositor's pan
        limits.
      </description>
      <arg name="dx" type="int"/>
      <arg name="dy" type="int"/>
    </request>

    <request name="zoom">
      <description summary="set the zoom factor">
        Set the camera zoom, clamped to the compositor's minimum and maximum
        zoom.
      </description>
      <arg name="factor" type="fixed"/>
    </request>

    <request name="focus_window">
      <description summary="reveal and focus a window">
        Pan the camera to reveal the window with the given id and give it focus.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="uint"/>
    </request>

    <request name="overview">
      <description summary="toggle fit-all overview">
        Enable (non-zero) or disable (zero) the fit-all overview for this
        output.
      </description>
      <arg name="enable" type="uint"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the canvas object">
        Destroy the canvas object. The compositor stops sending observer events
        to it.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
